我们看过了FILE结构体正常是怎么用的
so now that we've seen how file structure used during normal operation
现在探讨一下FILE结构是如何被滥用
let's explore how file structs can be abused
实现任意读或任意写
to gain arbitrary read or write
之前我们提到过
previously we mentioned that
FILE结构体内有8个指针
there are 8 pointers inside of the file struct
它们主要用于维持缓冲区状态
that are predominantly used to maintain a buffer state
这个缓冲区位于程序调用的字符串函数(如fwrite)
and this buffer sits in between the program calls to the string functions such as fwrite
与底层系统调用write之间
and the underlying syscall write
或者是底层系统调用read
or between the underlying syscall read
程序调用对应的字符串函数fread
and the program calling the corresponding string function fread
这些指针指示着缓冲区的状态
and these pointers indicate the state of that buffer
这些指针
and so the state of the pointers
确定是否需要，例如，刷新缓冲区
determines whether or not we need to for instance flush out a buffer
或者缓冲区是否需要重新填充
or whether that buffer needs to get refilled
我们需要调用read并用新数据填充它
we need to call read and fill it in with new data
如果它是一个读缓冲区的话
if it's a read buffer
我们还提到了在FILE结构体中有一个flags字段
now we also mentioned that there's a flags field in the file struct
这有一些你可以在flags字段中找到的值
some of the values that you can find in the flags field are shown here
flags字段的几个高有效位一直都是
the upper bits of the flags field will always contain
常量0xFBAD
the magic number 0xFBAD
所以当你第一次调用fopen
and so when you first call fopen
你会在flags的高有效位看到这个
this is what you'll find in the flags field for the upper bits
较低有效位决定了该文件的操作模式
the lower bits determine the kind of the mode of operation for that file
我们可以设置成不设缓冲区
so we could have a file that's unbuffered
在这种情况下
in which case
我们不会利用到之前描述的缓冲
we wouldn't even take advantage of that buffering that we described so far
还有操作模式
there are also modes of operation
有不能读或不能写的设置
where you cannot read or cannot write
它们存在的原因是
and the reason for that
当你考虑到这些记录着缓冲区状态的指针
is when you think about the pointers that exist to track the buffer state
如果你可以随意读写任何文件
if you could just arbitrarily read and write on any file
这些指针很容易混淆
it would be very easy for these pointers to get mixed up
然后进入非法状态
and get into an invalid state
所以在flags中存在显式的标志位
and so there are explicit mode bits that are exist in the flag
来拒绝读或写
that deny reading or deny writing
这并不是一个flags值的完整列表
now this is not an exhaustive list of values that can be found in the flag
所以一定要看看幻灯片底部的链接
so definitely check out the link at the bottom of the slide
你可以在那里找到源代码
where you can find the source code
然后查看所有可能的值
and see all the possible values yourself
还有一个我们之前没有提到的成员变量
now one of the other fields that we did not mention
但现在绝对值得一提
but is definitely worth mentioning now
就是_fileno 文件描述符变量
is the file number field
在FILE结构体中
so within the file struct
还有一个_fileno
there is also a file number
这个变量保存着文件描述符
and this file number holds the file descriptor
它用来记录目标文件
that exist there underpins kind of the file
所以当我们要写入文件时
so when we write to a file
先填充了这个缓冲区
it fills this buffer
缓冲区被填满时
when the buffer is filled
我们要flush数据到文件中
we need to flush it and write it out
我们调用write时
and when we call write
还是需要与文件描述符交互
we still need to interact with a file descriptor
所以与这个文件交互时要用到的文件描述符
so the file descriptor that will be used when interacting with this file
就是一个数字，存储在FILE结构体中
is stored just as a number in the file struct
记住这一点
keep that in mind
现在我们描述一下，我们想要获得任意的读写
now we describe that we want to gain arbitrary read and write
我们考虑一下这个流库是如何工作的
when we think about how the kind of streaming library works
它做了什么
what does it do
它要么从文件读到内存
well it either reads from a file to memory
读到在内存中的缓冲区
reads into that buffer that's located in memory
要么从内存中的缓冲区向外写入文件
or it writes from the buffer in memory out to a file
是否会读，以及读什么
and whether or not it reads and what it reads
或者是否会写，以及写什么
or whether or not it writes and what it writes
完全由这些缓冲区指针的状态决定
is determined entirely by the state of these buffer pointers
所以如果我们可以覆盖，或控制这些缓冲区指针
so if we can overwrite or gain control of these buffer pointers
我们就可以控制读写哪里
we can control where the read or write occurs
以及是否读写
and whether it occurs
要将文件读到任意内存
to read from a file to arbitrary memory
我们必须让缓冲区进入一个特定的状态
we have to get the buffer into a very specific state
我们必须设置flags值
we have to set the flag values
使文件允许读取
such that the file allows for reading
这说的通
that makes some sense
要将read_ptr设置为read_end
we need to set the read_ptr equal to the read_end
我们还要设置buf_base
we also need to set the buf_base
指向我们想要读到的位置
to be the location that we want to read into
buf_end必须是将要读取的结束点
the buf_end must be the end point of where we are going to read
最后
and finally
buf_end 减去 buf_base
buf_end minus buf_base
是缓冲区的大小，对于所有敏感的目标
which is the size of the buffer for all intensive purposes
它必须大于
must be larger than
我们想要读取的字节数
the number of bytes that we want to read
因为如果缓冲区相较于要读入的东西不够大
because if the buffer isn't big enough to read something in
库就会分配一个足够大的新缓冲区来执行此操作
the library will allocate a new buffer that is large enough to do so
所以我们要确保
so we want to make sure
buf_end - buf_base足够执行这个读操作
that buf_end minus buf_base is big enough to perform this read
这是正常操作时读的样子
so this is what reading looks like during normal operation
read_base等于read_buf
read_base is equal to read buff
read_end等于buf_end
read_end is equal to buf_end
read_ptr在中间
and read_ptr is somewhere in the middle
因为我们已经读过了一些东西
because we've read something
还有东西要读
and we still have ways to go
那么发生什么
so what happens
或者说我们要如何处理这些指针
or what do we have to do with these pointers
让它们进入一种状态
to get them into a state
使我们能将数据读到我们选择的位置
where we can read into a location of our choosing
这里有很多要求
there were a lot of requirements here
我们可以一条一条的过
so we could go line by line and move them around and see
但实际上我们不需要这么做
but in practice we don't have to actually do that
它可以是这样的
instead it can just look like this
每个指针都可以被设置为null
every pointer can get set to null
除了buf_base和buf_end
except for buf_base and buf_end
buf_base指向我们想要读入的位置的开头
buf_base should point to the beginning of where we want to read into
buf_end指向我们要读入的位置的末尾
buf_end should point to the end of where we want to read into
这就可以满足所有的条件
and this will satisfy all of the requirements
我们来看看实际情况
so let's see that in action
这里有一个有漏洞的c程序
so right here I have a vulnerable C program
我会很快地看一遍，以便理解发生了什么
will run through it real quick to understand what's going on
我们有一个全局win变量，默认设置为0
we have a global win variable by default it set to 0
我们有一个win函数，会打印出你赢了
we have a win function that prints out you win
如果它碰巧被调用的话
if it happens to get called
在main中
inside of main
我们直接泄露了win变量的地址
we are just given a leak of the win_var address
win_var的位置
the location of win_var
程序本身将调用fopen
the program itself is going to call fopen
打开一个名为secret_file的文件
and open a file named secret_file
打开它以供读取
it's going to be open for reading
然后立即给了我们覆盖FILE结构体的能力
we are then immediately given the ability to overwrite this file pointer
然后程序会fread这个文件
the program will then call fread on that file here
它将读入10个大小为1字节的成员
and it is going to read in 10 members of size 1
所以它会读取10个字节
so it's going to read in 10 bytes
它会把它读入缓冲区
and it's going to read it into a buffer
缓冲区就在栈上
that is sitting here on the stack
如果win_var碰巧发生了变化
in the event win_var happens to have changed
就会调用win函数
will call win
否则程序将退出
otherwise the program will exit
如果我们编译这个
so if we compile this
然后运行它
and run it
它会直接退出
it exits cleanly
如果我们给它一个足够长的值
and if we give it a long enough value
它会发生段错误
it will seg fault
我们来写一下利用脚本
so let's write and exploit for this
我们先开始一些样板代码
so we're gonna start off with some boiler plate code
导入pwn
from pwn import *
设置架构为amd64
context arch amd64
创建一个进程p
we're going to have some process p
它与a.out交互
that is going to interact with a.out
我要做的第一件事是
and the first thing I want to do is
获得泄露的信息
I want to grab the leak
所以我们会recv_until到
so we will receive until at
然后win_var_leak等于p.recvline
we will then say win_var_leak is equal to p receive line
我们去掉换行符
we drop the new line
以16进制数读入
and we read it in as hex
接下来我们要做的是
so next thing that we want to do is
我们想覆盖FILE结构体
we want to overwrite the file struct
那么我们要做什么呢
and so what do we do there
pwntools有一个非常有用的功能
well pwntools has an extremely helpful feature
我要马上用它
that I'm just going to use right out the gate
你可以调用FileStructure
so you can call file structure
这会返回一个python对象，它能表示FILE结构体
and this will give you a Python object that represents the file struct
我们在ipython中看一下
let's take a look at that in ipython here
这样你们就能明白我在说什么了
so you can kind of see what I'm talking about
我们写一个一样的东西
so we're gonna just write that exact same thing
能看到这个FP对象
and we see that this FP object has all of the same members
有和FILE结构体一样的成员变量
as the file struct that is used by the streams library
我们可以设定值
and we can set values
然后能在对象中看到它
then we see that is reflected in the object
如果我想导出这个FILE结构体的字节数据
now if I want to dump out the bytes of this file struct
我们可以调用bytes
we can call bytes on it
这就是原始字节，它能放到payload中
and there is the raw bytes that would be in a payload
我们可以这样使用这个文件结构对象
and so we can use this file structure object in this way
前提是如果我们需要自定义一些东西
if we need to set up something custom and specific
但利用文件结构体有一些常见的目的
but there's a couple common things that are done with file structure exploits
比如我们现在讨论的任意读和写
such as the reading write that we're talking about right now
所以我们还可以更简单
and so we can actually do one thing easier than this
我们需要发送一个payload
we're going to need to send some kind of a payload
这个payload的定义只需通过fp.read
all this payload can be defined by doing a file structure read
我们想读到win_var_leak
and we want to read to the win_var_leak
下一个参数是想要读取的字节长度
and the next value is the number of bytes that I want to read
这个值需要大一点
now this value needs to be larger
要比读取的值大
than the fread value
要读取的值长度是10
so the fread value is 10
我们就设一个20吧
so let's set this to 20
然后执行p.interactive
then we'll do a p.interactive
然后调用它
and call it good
我们先给利用脚本可执行权限
so let's make that exploit script executable
运行一下
and let's run it
我们看到了Calling fread
and we see there was calling fread
但这个程序没退出
but the program hasn't exited
现在我阻塞在这个提示这里
right now I'm blocked on the prompt here
那么发生了什么
so what's happening
如果我输入足够多的a
well if I type enough a's
它就会输出“你赢了”
it says you win
为什么要打这些a呢
okay so why did I need to type those a's
因为这个文件结构的默认值中
well the default value for a file structure here
_fileno的值是0
for the file number is 0
如果我们打印出
so if we print out
_fileno
the file number
再运行一次
we run this again
我们看到_fileno是0
we see that the file number is 0
这表示标准输入
which is going to be standard in
所以对于这个fread
so this fread
尽管代码中的FILE指针
even though this file pointer here in the source
指向打开的secret_file
was opened was opening secret_file
通过修改_fileno
by setting the file number
我们让这个read读取标准输入
we made this read come from standard in
然后不再读入到栈上的这个缓冲区
and then instead of writing to this buffer here that sitting on the stack
我们这样修改这些指针后
we are able to change the pointers such that
让它覆盖了win_var变量
it overwrote this win_var
现在如果你想看它的细节
now if you want to see the specifics of it
我们可以在我们的利用脚本中输出这个文件结构
we can print out the file structure right here in our exploit ahead of time
我们看到发生了什么
and what do we see happened
flags的值并不重要
well the flags value didn't matter
我们不需要设置它
we didn't have to set it
所有这些指针都被设为0
all of these pointers were set to zero
唯一重要的是buf_base和buf_end
the only ones that mattered were buf_base and buf_end
它们被设置成我们需要的地址
those got set to the address that we need
所以当fread被调用时
so then when fread was called
我们从fileno 0读入
we read from the file number here 0
所以我们从标准输入读入
so we read from standard in
然后我们读入到这个缓冲区，这个攻击者指定的缓冲区
and we read it in to this buffer this buffer that we defined
很酷
pretty cool
任意写非常类似
so so we can do something very similar here with writing
所以我们有一个需求清单
so we have a list of requirements
我们需要设置flags以允许写入
we need to set the flag value to allow for writing
我们需要将write_base设置为
we need to set the write_base equal to the
我们要写入内存的开头
beginning of memory that we want to write out
write_ptr指向试图写入内存区的末尾
the write_ptr terminates that region of memory that we're trying to write out
因为从write_base到write_ptr的距离
because remember the distance from write_base to write_ptr
在正常的缓冲区中
in a normal functioning buffer
表示已经写入
is the bytes that have already been written
但还没有保存到文件的数据
but haven't been flushed out to the file
我们想定义我们想泄漏的
and so we want to define what we want to leak
或者说我们想写出到文件的
or what we want to write out to the file
在write_base和write_ptr这两个指针之间
in between those two pointers write_base and write_ptr
第四个条件看起来有点武断
now this fourth requirement is a little bit arbitrary
基于我们所展示的
like based upon what we've kind of shown
这些指针在缓冲区的作用
as far as what the pointers do with the buffer
但在实现代码中
but in the implementation
read_end在写缓冲区中，有一种特殊的用途
read_end has kind of a special use case for write buffers
所以我们只能接受
and so we're just kind of accept
read_end必须等于write_base
that read_end must equal write_base
有一个特定的检查
there's a specific check that occurs
我们要确保这个检查返回true
and we want to make sure that this holds true
才能flush缓冲区数据
to cause the buffer to flush
最后一点
and then lastly
buf_end - buf_base
buf_end minus buf_base
必须大于我们想要写入的字节数
must be larger than the number of bytes that we want to write
在实现代码中
again in the implementation
buf_end减去buf_base是预留缓冲区的大小
buf_end minus buf_base is the size of the reserve buffer
所以我们要确保缓冲区足够大
and so we want to make sure that the buffer is big enough
在理论上
in theory
我们表示的理论上的缓冲区
our theoretical buffer here that we're representing
足够容纳我们要写的东西
is big enough to hold what it is we're trying to write out
所以这个也必须成立
and so that this must hold true as well
在写的情况
in the case of writing
这是正常的缓冲区
so here's our normal operating buffer
我们看到buf_end是结束，buf_base是开始
we see that buf_end is the end buf_base is the beginning
我们需要足够大的缓冲区来容纳我们要写的内容
so we need the buffer to be large enough to hold what we're trying to write
write_base为开始，write_end为结束
write_base is the beginning write_end is the end
write_ptr在中间的某个地方
and write_ptr is chilling somewhere here in the middle
因为我们假设
because we're assuming
已经向缓冲区写了一些要被flush到文件的数据
that we're in a state where we have written some bytes to the buffer that need to be flushed out
但仍然有空间写入额外的字节
but there's still room to write additional byte
那么要控制这个需要发生什么呢
so what needs to happen in order to control this and
让它写入到我们选择的地址
write out a memory address of our choosing
这并不难
once again it's not that hard
它并不像你最初认为的那样复杂
it's not nearly as complicated as the requirements might make you think initially
我们设置read_end和write_base
if we set read_end and write_base
都指向要写入内存的开头
to the beginning of the memory that we want to write out
将write_ptr置为该值的末尾
we set write_ptr to the end of that value
其他都为零
and everything else to null
我们就可以写出一个secret值或我们选择的值
then we will be able to write out a secret value or a value of our choosing
我们快速看一下
so let's take a quick look at that
这儿有一个有写漏洞的程序
here we have a vulnerable write example
我们有一个全局的secret_message
we have a global secret_message
这是栈上的一个字符串
that is a string on the stack here
就是SECRET_FLAG_VALUE
it just says secret flag value
在main中
inside of main
给我们泄漏了secret_message地址
we are given a leak of the address of secret_message
程序本身将打开/dev/null进行写入
the program itself will open /dev/null for writing
用fopen打开它
just going to open it with fopen
所以我们在这里使用了流函数
so we are using that streams functionality here
它返回一个FILE结构体指针
which returns a file struct pointer
然后就让我们能覆盖这个结构体
we're then allowed to immediately overwrite that file struct
然后程序将fwrite它
the program will then call fwrite on the file pointer
它将读入40个大小为1字节的成员
and it's going to read in 40 members of size 1
所以它会读取40字节
so it's going to read in 40 bytes
然后它就会退出
and then it will exit
我们在这里编写一个利用脚本
so let's write an exploit script here
我们从样板代码开始
we'll start off with our typical boiler plate
要有一个进程p
we're gonna have some process p
我应该先编译一下这个
I should probably compile this
如果我们运行它
if we run it
与第一个例子非常相似
very similar to the first example
如果我们给它足够的输入，它就会出现段错误
if we give it enough input it will seg fault
我要做的第一件事是捕捉泄漏
now the first thing I want to do is capture the leak
所以我们会recvuntil
so we'll receive until at
然后recvline
then we will receive line
去掉换行符
drop the new line
转成int
convert it to an INT
按16进制解析它
as hex
它就是
and that is going to be
secret_val_leak
the secret_val_leak
现在我们有了这个
now that we have that
我们需要覆盖文件结构体
we need to overwrite the file struct
同样，我们可以使用pwntools
again we can use pwntools
和之前非常类似
and very similar to
之前我们用的fp.read
before we had fp.read
实际上还有一个fp.write
there is in fact an fp.write
我们可以指定写在哪里
where we can specify where we want to write
写多少字节
and then how many bytes
在这个例子中，程序想写40
in this case the challenge wants to write 40
所以这里写60
so we'll write 60 there
这就是我们的payload
that will be our payload
然后我们发送payload
and then we will send the payload
然后开转成交互式会话
have a interactive session
所以
so
我们给这个利用脚本可执行权限
we make the exploit executable
运行这个利用脚本
we run the exploit
我们在这里看到
and we see here that
很抱歉
sorry about that
我们运行这个脚本
we run the exploit
我们看到秘密值泄露出来了
and we see that the secret value is leaked out
以及紧跟其后的大量字节
along with a large number of bytes that immediately follow it
所以我们可以构造一个FILE结构体
and so we were able to craft a file structure
它将让这个fwrite调用
that turned this fwrite call
不再将这个缓冲区内容写入到/dev/null
instead of writing this empty buffer to /dev/null
我们可以把它改成
we were able to change it such that
让这个fwrite，输出这个secret_message到屏幕
this fwrite wrote out this secret_message or secret flag value
为了完整起见
and then just for completeness sake
我们也打印出用在payload的文件结构体
let's also print out the file structure here that we used for our payload
我们看到这和之前描述的完全一致
and we see that this follows exactly what was described earlier
设置了flags
the flag values are set
read_end 等于write_base
read_end equals write_base
然后write_ptr在write_base之后一段距离处
and then the write_ptr is some distance after write_base
这实际上就是这里的60指定的
that's actually what the 60 here is specifying
我说的这个值需要稍大一些
when I say that this value needs to be larger
这是在定义大小
this is defining the size or the distance I should say
或者说write_base和write_ptr之间的距离
between write_base and write_ptr
因为输出的东西
because remember what is actually getting dumped out
是从write_base开始
is starting at write_base
到write_ptr结束
and then ending at write_ptr
这就是这里需要一个size值的原因
and so that's why that size value is needed here
但我们能看到
but we see that
FILE结构体利用的核心思路非常直接
file structure exploits at their core are pretty straightforward
当使用像pwntools这样的工具时，实现起来也很简单
and relatively simple to pull off when you're using something like pwntools